Guide to the Clive L. DuVal papers, 1960-1994
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Clive L. DuVal papers
1960-1994
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Clive L. DuVal, 1912-2002
C0007
78 linear feet (173 boxes)
The papers in this collection document Clive DuVal's career as a Democratic delegate and senator in the Virginia General Assembly. The materials contained within - including correspondence, campaign pamphlets, legislative files, press releases and constituents newsletters - provide a glimpse of Virginia state politics and legislative issues during his first two decades of tenure starting in 1966, with the bulk of materials dating from 1974-1990. Legislative issues represented in this collection include the Equal Rights Amendment; the lottery; regulation of public utilities, mining operation, and nuclear power; conflict of interest rulings; environmental conservation; transportation; and higher education in Northern Virginia, especially pertaining to George Mason University and Northern Virginia Community College. Among the most notable files are those relating to the Revision of the Virginia State Constitution (1968-1969). The correspondence and campaign materials reflect platform issues and alliances within the Democratic party, while the series on the McClean Citizens Association and the Virginians for Dulles contain records on important citizens action groups in Northern Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Clive DuVal in 1989-1997.
Biographical Information
Born June 20, 1912, in New York City, Clive L. DuVal 2nd, graduated summa cum laude in 1935 from Yale University where he was a member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1938, he received an LL.B. from Yale University Law School. While a law student, he edited the Yale Law Journal.
DuVal spent most of lengthy career in public service. Serving from 1942-1946 as a U.S. Naval officer, he was assigned to an aircraft carrier in the Pacific during World War II. During his military service, he received a Commendation Medal, the Asiatic-Pacific Ribbon with five battle stars, and a Presidential Unit Citation. From 1951 until 1959 when he entered private law practice, he served as Special Assistant to the Undersecretary of the Army (1951-1952), Special Assistant to the Assistant Secretary of the Defense (1953), Assistant General Counsel (international Affairs) in the Department of the Defense (1953-1955), and General Counsel for the U.S. Information Agency (1955-1959). In 1959, he was Associate General Counsel for the President's Committee to Study the United States Military Assistance Program.
After joining the Arlington, Virginia, law firm of Milbank, Tweed, Hadley, and McCloy in 1959, DuVal successfully ran as a Democratic candidate for the Virginia House of Delegates in 1965. During three terms as a Delegate, he sponsored or helped bring passage of legislation relating to workman's compensation issues, the protection of historic landmarks, tax and election reform, and participated in the revision of the Virginia State Constitution in 1969. His leadership in conservation was recognized when he was chosen outstanding legislator by the National Wildlife Federation in 1969.
After unsuccessfully running for the U.S. House of Representatives, 10th District of Virginia, in 1968, he defeated an incumbent to gain a seat in the Virginia Senate in 1971. Senator DuVal tried twice without success to gain his party's nomination to the U.S. Senate in 1970 and 1978. He has been elected to successive four-year terms in the Virginia Senate since 1971.
During his tenure in the Virginia Senate, DuVal served on numerous committees, including Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources; Commerce and Labor; Finance; Privileges and Elections; and Rules. He has been most noted for being the sponsor of the Equal Rights Amendment in the Virginia Senate. His legislative interests reflect a concern for consumers, for the environment, and for the constituents of his Northern Virginia district. He served as Chairman of Virginians for Dulles, a citizens lobby to reduce noise levels and traffic at National Airport in Arlington.
In 1940 DuVal married Susan Holdredge Bontecou. They had four children, Susan, Clive, David, and Daniel. Longtime residents of McLean, Virginia, they restored and live in historic "Salona," the house where President James Madison and his wife, Dolley, sought refuge during the burning of Washington in the War of 1812.
Scope and Content
The materials in this collection contain information concerning the Virginia state legislative and political processes. Significant legislative issues represented in the collection include the Equal Rights Amendment; the lottery; regulation of public utilities, mining operation, and nuclear power; conflict of interest rulings; environmental conservation; transportation; and higher education in Northern Virginia, especially pertaining to George Mason University and Northern Virginia Community College. Among the most notable files are those relating to the Revision of the Virginia State Constitution (1968-1969). The correspondence and campaign materials reflect platform issues and alliances within the Democratic party, while the series on the McClean Citizens Association and the Virginians for Dulles contain records on important citizens action groups in Northern Virginia.
Series 1: Correspondence contains letters written between Clive DuVal and constituents, state and national politicians, staff members, friends and acquaintances. Topics of correspondence include recommendations for service academy appointments, college admissions, and jobs; responses to invitations; instructions to staff members; and constituent concerns such as the environment, spousal abuse, traffic, Great Falls improvements, and historic landmarks.
Series 2: Legislative Files contains research for drafts and printed copies of legislation sponsored by or supported by Clive DuVal during service in the Virginia House of Delegates and the Senate, notably the Equal Rights Amendment, the Lottery Bill, nuclear regulation, public utility regulation, tax benefits for the elderly and handicapped, pesticide controls, beverage container law, mining industry regulation, transportation and highways, and higher education in Northern Virginia (Community College and George Mason University). Subseries 2.2 consists of studies on issues that are not necessarily linked to a specific bill. Such studies were used as background for developing a legislative agenda as well as for taking part in informed debate. Included in the studies are the major working files for the revision of the Virginia State Constitution (1968-1969) as well as information on such topics as the environment and nuclear energy regulation.
Series 3: Campaign Materials contains notes for speeches, legislator survey responses, fund-raising files, reports of campaign contributions and expenditures, declaration of candidacy certificates, election tallies, brochures, position papers, and press releases and clipping files.
Series 4: McLean Citizens Association documents DuVal's work as president of the McLean Citizens Association (MCA). The records portray efforts to reverse a rezoning decision made by the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors as requested by developer Sheldon Magazine. Magazine sought the rezoning for the purpose of constructing apartment units in an area known as Merrywood located on Route 123. Development of this tract of land was viewed by the MCA and others as a threat to the environment of the Potomac Gorge located above the Key Bridge between Virginia and the District of Columbia. The matter went before a Grand Jury in 1962 which examined the potential involvement of County officials in criminal activity regarding the rezoning application. Records include correspondence, meeting minutes, resolutions, records of public hearings, petitions in opposition to rezoning, legal research, legal documents, press releases, news clippings, photographs, and slides.
Series 5: Virginians for Dulles documents DuVal's work as president of Virginians for Dulles (VFD), a citizen action group that sought to reduce aircraft noise and emmissions by rerouting air traffic from Washington National to Dulles International Airport. The series includes meeting minutes, correspondence between VFD board members, financial records, telephone messages, and by-laws for Virginians for Dulles and other groups seeking to mitigate airport nuisances. Also included are legal briefs of suits filed by VFD against Washington National Airport and transcripts of testimony before the Aviation Subcommittee of the US House Committee on Public Works and Transportation.
Series 6: Press Releases and Constituent Newsletters contains official press releases on legislative and campaign topics. The newsletters include published reports on legislation in progress, activities of the General Assembly, and anecdotes about the legislation session. From 1966-1987 the newsletter was titled "DuVal's Democratic Daily, and in 1988 its title was changed to "The DuVal Dispatch."
Series 7: Printed Materials contains various published journals dealing with the environment, constitutional reform in Virginia, or nuclear regulation.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 6 series by subject; each series is divided into subseries by date, and each subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject/title.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1973-1994 (Box 1-24)
Series 2: Legislative Files, 1966-1992 (Box 25-73)
Series 3: Campaign Materials, 1960-1994 (Box 74-76)
Series 4: McLean Citizens Association, 1960-1962 (Box 77)
Series 5: Virginians for Dulles, 1968-1981 (Box 78-80)
Series 6: Press Releases and Constituent Newsletters, 1966-1987 (Box 81)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1963-1989 (Box 81)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collection and Archives also holds many other collections on Northern Virginia politics and government as well as the records of Virginians for Dulles, a citizens action group for which DuVal served as president. For additional materials on Virginians for Dulles see the finding aid for the.
Index Terms
Persons:
DuVal, Clive L., (Clive Livingston), 1912-2002.
Corporate Names:
Virginia. Commission on Constitutional Revision.; Virginia. General Assembly.; Virginians for Dulles.
Geographical Names:
Virginia, Northern--Politics and government.
Subjects:
Environmental policy--Virginia.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1973-1994
  This series contains letters written between Clive DuVal and constituents, state and national politicians, staff members, friends and acquaintances. Topics of correspondence include recommendations for service academy appointments, college admissions, and jobs; responses to invitations; instructions to staff members; and constituent concerns such as the environment, spousal abuse, traffic, Great Falls improvements, and historic landmarks.
  - General Correspondence, October, November, and December 1973; January 19, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, February 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, February 1974 A (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, February 1974 B (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, February 1974 C (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, March 1974 A (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, March 1974 B (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, April 1974 A (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, April 1974 B (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, May and June 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, August and September 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, October, November, and December 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence: Richmond, January and February 1975 A (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence: Richmond, January and February 1975 B (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence: Richmond, January and February 1975 C (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence: Richmond, January and February 1975 D (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, January and February 1975 A (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, January and February 1975 B (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, February 1975 A (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, February 1975 B (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, March 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, April, May, June, July, and August 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, August 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, September, October, November, December 1975; January 8, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, September 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, October 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, November 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, December 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, January 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 19, 1976 - February 29, 1976 A (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, January 19, 1976 - February 29, 1976 B (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, February and March 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, March 1-17, 1976 A (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, March 1-17, 1976 B (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, March 1-17, 1976 C (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, April 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, March 18, 1976 - June 30, 1976 A (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, March 18, 1976 - June 30, 1976 B (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, May 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, June 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, July 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, August 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, September 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, October 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, November 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, December 1976 A (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, December 1976 B (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1977 A (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1977 B (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1977 C (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, March 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, April 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, April - December 1977 A (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, April - December 1977 B (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, April - December 1977 C (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, May 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, June 1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, July 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, August 1977 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, September 1977 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, October 1977 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, November 1977 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, December 1977 A (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, December 1977 B (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1978 A (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1978 B (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1978 C (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1978 D (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, April - May 1978 A (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, April - May 1978 B (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1978 A (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1978 B (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, June 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, July 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, August 1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, August 1978 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, September 1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, November 1978 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, December 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, January 1979 A (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 1979 B (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, February 1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, March 1979 A (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, March 1979 B (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, April 1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, May 1979 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, June 1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, July 1979 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, August 1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, September 1979 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, October 1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, November 1979 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, December 1979 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence: General Assembly, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 1982 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, February 1982 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, March 1982 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, April 1982 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, May 1982 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, June 1982 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1982 A (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1982 B (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1982 A (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1982 B (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1983 A (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1983 B (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1983 C (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, May - July 1983 A (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, May - July 1983 B (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, August - October 1983 A (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, August - October 1983 B (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1983 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1984 A (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1984 B (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, June - August 1984 A (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, June - August 1984 B (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1984 A (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1984 B (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, January - September 1985 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1985 A (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1985 B (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, May - August 1985 A (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, May - August 1985 B (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1985 A (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1985 B (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 1986 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, February 1986 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, March 1986 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, April 1986 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, May 1986 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, June 1986 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, July 1986 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, August 1986 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, September 1986 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, October 1986 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, November 1986 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, December 1986 A (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, December 1986 B (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, January 1987 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, February 1987 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, March 1987 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, April 1987 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, May 1987 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, June 1987 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, July 1987 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, August 1987 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, September 1987 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, October 1987 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, November 1987 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, December 1987 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, January 1-19, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 20-29, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, February 1-14, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, February 15-29 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, March 1988 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, April 1988 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, May 1988 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, June 1988 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, July 1988 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, August 1988 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence (CLD), June 1989 (Box 101, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence (CLD), May 1989 (Box 101, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence (CLD), April 1989 (Box 101, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence (CLD), March 1989 (Box 101, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, February 1989 (Box 103, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January 1989 (Box 103, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, December 1988 (Box 103, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, November 1988 (Box 103, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, October 1988 (Box 104, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, September 1988 (Box 104, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with State Offices and General Assembly, undated (Box 111, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, September 1989 (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, August 1989 (Box 119, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, July 1989 (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence (CLD), July 1989 (Box 119, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 142, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, pt 1, July 1990 (Box 153, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, pt 2, July 1990 (Box 153, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, June 1990 (Box 153, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, pt 1, May 1990 (Box 153, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, pt 2, May 1990 (Box 153, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, pt 1, April 1990 (Box 153, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, pt 2, April 1990 (Box 153, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, February 1990 (Box 153, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, pt 1, March 1990 (Box 153, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, pt 2, March 1990 (Box 153, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, pt 1, January 1990 (Box 153, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, pt 2, January 1990 (Box 153, Folder 16)